Finding Aid for Richard D. Ahern Papers, 1956-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard D. Ahern Papers 1956-2004, 1956-1980
Ahern, Richard D.
1 oversize folder
3 linear feet
05121 Aa 2 Ac
Papers of Richard Ahern, Ann Arbor architect and community planner for over 40 years, and instructor at Lawrence Institute of Technology from 1977 to 1981. Collection consists mainly of documents from Ahern’s professional projects, as well as his teaching career at Lawrence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the estate of Richard Ahern (donor no. 9620 ), July 26, 2005.
The collection is open to research.
Richard Ahern was born on the 4th of July 1927 in Medford, Massachusetts, and spent his early years in Washington, D.C. He was in the U.S. Navy from 1945 to 1946, after which he attended the University of Maryland for one year. Ahern then transferred to Massachusetts Institute of Technology, where he majored in architecture and received a B.S. in 1950. The next two years were spent studying at the Technische Hochschule in Austria, where he received a doctorate in technology. He apprenticed with two architectural firms in Washington, D.C. from 1952 to 1954, taught as an Assistant Professor of Architecture at Kent State University from 1954 to 1957, and worked for the City Plan Commission for the City of Detroit from 1957 to 1960, and again in 1962.
Ahern moved to Ann Arbor in 1962, following a year-long trip during which he visited approximately 20 countries in Asia. Soon after his arrival, he moved into a large unimproved studio space at 336 1/2 South State Street, where he would continue to live and work for the remaining 42 years of his life.
Professionally, Ahern worked on numerous projects that combined planning and architecture, such as a study of alternatives for the Ann Arbor Airport and designing residential communities for Clarkston and West Bloomfield. From 1966 to 1970, he also served as a planning consultant for the town of Bloomfield Hills, where he advocated for a housing style known as cluster court housing. He was also interested in planning for the central Ann Arbor area, where he envisioned "podium parking" and high-rise architecture as solutions to modern congestion problems.
Ahern also worked as an artist, producing thousands of drawings of buildings and places around the world during his lifetime, many of which were published as popular lithographs. From 1977 to 1981, he also taught architecture and planning at Lawrence Institute of Technology in Southfield.
Ahern was very interested in world peace, and he was active with groups including the Alliance for Democracy and the Green Party. His 1981 curriculum vitae listed "part-time, self-disciplined studies in Systems Philosophy, War and Peace, Ethics, etc." as ongoing since 1969.
In a 2002 article (included in Box 1 of the collection), Ahern described himself as "schizoergic," "an independent cuss," and "the world's oldest rock and roller," among other things. He died in 2004 at the age of 76, leaving behind a large volume of personal files on the numerous activities that engaged him throughout his life.
The Richard Ahern papers consist of writings, correspondence, sketches and designs relating to his professional career as an architect, community planner, and educator. The collection provides insight into Ahern's creative and philosophical growth as a designer and planner, and provides snapshots of the growth of several Michigan communities in the 1960s and 1970s.
When they were donated, the Richard Ahern papers contained a large volume of newspaper clippings, publications, and similar research material that Ahern collected in preparation for each of his projects. Although only those documents that directly reflect Ahern's work were kept (a small fraction of the original volume), much of the overall organization schema was maintained.
The Richard Ahern papers are divided into five series: Personal, Early Designs and Sketches, Architecture, Planning, and Teaching.
Subjects:
Ahern, Richard D.; Architects--Michigan.; Ann Arbor Airport.; Bloomfield Hills (Mich.); Clarkston (Mich.); Lawrence Institute of Technology.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Airports--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Superior (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Traverse City (Mich.); Boblo Island Amusement Park (Ont.); Planning--Michigan.
- Personal
  Personal consists of items related to Ahern that are not directly related to any of the other series.
  - Biographical information 1976, 1977, 1981, 2002, and 2004 (Box 1)
  - "The Process (A Philosophy)" with illustrations (undated) (Box 1)
- Early Designs and Sketches
  Early Designs and Sketches includes drawings that Ahern made prior to approximately 1962 and which were not part of any identifiable professional project.
  - Sydney Opera House contest entry 1956 (Box 1)
  - Houses, motels, other residence types, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Churches and towers (Box 1)
  - City planning (Box 1)
  - Memorials, floats, displays, and Kent State Library (Box 1)
  - "Art doodles", landscape, facades, objects (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: Ahern's sketches of Asia 1961 (Box 1)
- Architecture
  Architecture includes projects in which Ahern was involved exclusively (or primarily) as an architect, and for which he produced architectural drawings. These items were separated in Ahern's personal files as "Architectural Commissions."
  - Bob-Lo Pavilion, Detroit 1958-1960
    - Correspondence, notes, etc. (Box 1)
    - "A Preliminary Study" (Box 1)
    - Sketches and report pages, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Design presentation notebook (Box 1)
  - The Blind Pig, Ann Arbor, correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
  - Woischwill Apartments (Box 1)
  - "Toward A Vietnamese Architecture" (Box 1)
- Planning
  Planning includes projects in which Ahern played a planner role, although he also created architectural drawings for a number of the projects. As they were during Ahern's life, these files are organized by geographic location and project. Of particular interest are a thorough 1975 impact report on the proposed Ann Arbor Airport, a "new town" planned for Superior Township in 1964, a 15-year-plus effort to recreate a wedge of land at the corner of Washtenaw and Forest Avenues in Ann Arbor, and Ahern's writings on Ann Arbor parking issues beginning in the late 1970s.
  - Afghanistan
    - "Suggestions on Tourism in Afghanistan" 1961 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor
    - Critique of Central City High Rise and Parking Report 1965 (Box 1)
    - Newsletter: "Crisis, '71 Briarwood" 1971 (Box 1)
    - Commentary on Ann Arbor Development Plan 1973 (Box 1)
    - Downtown and parking 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Property at Forest Avenue and Washtenaw Avenue
      - Ann Arbor Apartment Trust
        - Drawings 1963 (Box 1)
        - Preliminary plans 1963 (Box 1)
        - Washtenaw Place / Washtenaw Towers 1964 (Box 1)
        - "Thirty High" proposal 1965 (Box 1)
      - Jack Stegman Project
        - Washtenaw Terrace Maisonettes 1976 (Box 1)
        - Sketches circa 1976-1977 (Box 1)
        - Correspondence 1976 (Box 1)
        - Meeting notes 1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Airport
    - Grant application 1974 (Box 1)
    - TransPlan correspondence, proposal and work allocation schedule 1973-1975 (Box 1)
    - Report drafts and working copies (Box 1)
    - Report replaced sections (Box 1)
    - Master Plan Phase 1 Executive Summary Report 1975 (Box 1)
    - Master Plan, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Matrix for evaluation of alternatives (Box 1)
    - Ahern's report and commentaries 1975 (Box 1)
    - City Council presentation and letter to the editor 1977, 1980 (Box 1)
    - 3x5 notes and color slides of various airports (Box 3)
      (located in note card box at end of Box 3)
  - Bloomfield Hills
    - Proposal, contract and billing statements 1966-1970 (Box 2)
    - Cluster court housing 1966, undated (Box 2)
    - Sketches for City Hall 1967 (Box 2)
    - "The Village Center" baseline maps (Box 2)
    - Village Center Study 1967 (Box 2)
      (drawing)
    - Recommendation on Wajim building 1968 (Box 2)
    - Woodward Corridor 1967-1969 (Box 2)
    - Comments on Review of Proposed Apartments on Long Lake Road 1970 (Box 2)
    - Zoning ordnance recommendations 1967-1969, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Zoning ordnance recommendations 1967-1968 (Box 2)
      (drafts and working copies)
    - General planning suggestions 1967-1969, undated (Box 2)
    - Response to request for re-zoning on Tiverton Road 1969
      - Advisory References (Box 2)
      - #1, "Preliminary Statement of Urban Design Criteria.. ." (Box 2)
      - #2, "Proposed Addition and Modifications to Zoning Ordnance" 1966 (Box 2)
      - #3 and #3A, Proposed zoning for cluster court housing 1966 (Box 2)
      - #4, # 4A, and #4B, Composite zoning amendments and cluster housing 1966 (Box 2)
      - #5, "A Survey of Current and Potential Brush Fires, Areas of Concern, and Present and Impending Crises" 1967 (Box 2)
      - #6, "The Commercial Core of the City.. ." (Box 2)
      - #14, Bloomfield Center property (Box 2)
    - Handwritten drafts and notes (Box 2)
    - Sketches of downtown land use plan (Folder 1)
    - Benedict Farm/Woodward Avenue area 1976 (Box 2)
  - Clarkston
    - Correspondence 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Snapshot photographs of land (Box 2)
    - Deer Lake logo sketches (Box 2)
    - Proposed Planned Unit Development Regulations 1967
      - Handwritten drafts, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Typewritten drafts (Box 2)
      - Final draft (Box 2)
    - House plan sketches, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Site plan options (Box 2)
    - Site planning sketches (in Oversize folder) (Box 2)
  - Detroit
    - "A Report on the 1958 Report of the Detroit Rapid Transit Commission" 1958 (Box 2)
    - "Plans for the Future of the Central City" 1960 or 1962 (Box 2)
    - International Village, alternate deck proposals 1962 (Box 2)
  - Southfield
    - Preliminary study and correspondence 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Industrial park maps and sketches c. 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - "Analysis of Proposed Setback Requirements" 1966 (Box 2)
    - Zuckerman Property 1965 (Box 2)
  - Superior Township
    - "Proposal for a New Town" 1964 (Box 2)
    - New Town / Vreerland property correspondence 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Remarks on growth 1980 (Box 2)
  - Traverse City
    - Correspondence 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Report on Development Potential 1964
      - Handwritten drafts, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Working copy (Box 3)
      - Final copy (Box 3)
    - Waterfront study 1965 (Box 3)
      (drawings)
  - Washington, D.C.
    - Ahern on proposed zoning 1956 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw County
    - "The Urban Environment: Design Alternatives" 1964 and population matrix (Box 3)
  - West Bloomfield
    - Three Generation House 1962 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, etc. 1965, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Willow Run Airport
    - TransPlan Proposal 1974 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Projects
    - General (Box 3)
    - Projects with John Helveston and Jack Stegeman 1979, 3x5 notes, sketches and slides (Box 3)
- Teaching
  Finally, Teaching includes documents created during the course of Ahern's brief career at the Lawrence Institute of Technology. Items included in this series include class lists and photographs, notes on Ahern's classes, and numerous writings by Ahern explaining his philosophies on grading and education.
  - Class Notes
    - 1977 undated (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
      (notecards)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ahern writings on grading, education, etc. 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Ahern on architecture 1978 (Box 3)
  - Copies of grade sheets 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    (blank)
  - Student feedback (Box 3)
  - Various class documents, calendars and matrices 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)